<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: announcements | JS Balrog]]></title>
  <link href="http://jsbalrog.github.io/blog/categories/announcements/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jsbalrog.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-09T11:24:02-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://jsbalrog.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ted Jenkins]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Stick it to DRM]]></title>
    <link href="http://jsbalrog.github.io/blog/2014/05/06/stick-it-to-drm/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-06T08:10:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://jsbalrog.github.io/blog/2014/05/06/stick-it-to-drm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As an Open-Source advocate, DRM&mdash;<em>Digital Rights Management</em>, or a way to control access to
material in digital format&mdash;has long been a sticking point for me. International Day Against
DRM is Tuesday, May 6th. Several publishing houses are marking this day with great discounts.
One such publisher that I really like, Packt (pronounced &ldquo;packed&rdquo;) Publishing, is offering
anything in their catalog for $10 during May 6th. Pretty sweet, huh?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Here&rsquo;re the details from
Packt Publishing&rsquo;s press release:</p>

<p>&ldquo;Packt Publishing firmly believes that you should be able to read and interact with
your content when you want, where you want, and how you want – to that end they
have been advocates of DRM-free content since their very first eBook was published
back in 2004.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;To show their continuing support for <a href="https://www.defectivebydesign.org/dayagainstdrm">Day Against DRM</a>,
Packt Publishing is offering all its DRM-free content at $10 for 24 hours only on May
6th eBooks and Videos at www.packtpub.com.&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Our top priority at Packt has always been to meet the evolving needs of developers in the most practical way possible, while at the same time protecting the hard work of
our authors. DRM-free content continues to be instrumental in making that happen, providing the flexibility and freedom that is essential for an efficient and enhanced
learning experience. That’s why we’ve been DRM-free from the beginning – we’ll never put limits on the innovation of our users.&rdquo;</p>

<p>– Dave Maclean, Managing Director</p>

<p>Advocates of Day Against DRM are invited to spread the word and celebrate on May 6th by exploring the full range of DRM-free content at <a href="http://www.packtpub.com">packtpub.com</a>, where all eBooks and Videos will be $10 for 24 hours.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
